<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The second manifesto of Marcus Antonius de Dominis, Archbishop of Spalatio [sic] wherein for his better satisfaction, and the satisfaction of others, he publikely repenteth, and recanteth his former errors, and setteth downe the cause of his leauing England, and all Protestant countries, to returne vnto the Catholicke Romane Church: written by himselfe in Latine, and translated into English by M. G.K.</title>
            <author>De Dominis, Marco Antonio, 1560-1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20602</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7001</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109786</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845431</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845431</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10328</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20602)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10328)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1377:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The second manifesto of Marcus Antonius de Dominis, Archbishop of Spalatio [sic] wherein for his better satisfaction, and the satisfaction of others, he publikely repenteth, and recanteth his former errors, and setteth downe the cause of his leauing England, and all Protestant countries, to returne vnto the Catholicke Romane Church: written by himselfe in Latine, and translated into English by M. G.K.</title>
                  <author>De Dominis, Marco Antonio, 1560-1624.</author>
                  <author>G. K., fl. 1623.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[52] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Guilliaume Houius, with permission of superiours,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Liege :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Latin original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴ G² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>De Dominis, Marco Antonio, 1560-1624.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10328:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10328:1"/>
            <p>THE SECOND <hi>MANIFESTO</hi> OF <hi>MAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CVS ANTONIVS DE DOMINIS,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Spalatto:</hi> wherein for his better ſatisfaction, and the ſatisfaction of others, he publikely repenteth, and recanteth his former errors, and ſetteth downe the cauſe of his leauing ENGLAND, and all Proteſtant Countries, to returne vnto the Catholicke Romane Church: <hi>Written by himſelfe in Latine, and</hi> tranſlated into Engliſh by <hi>M. G.</hi> K.</p>
            <bibl>LVKE 22. 26.</bibl>
            <q>Egreſſus foras fleuit amare.</q>
            <figure/>
            <p>LIEGE. By <hi>Guilliaume Houius,</hi> with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Superiours.</p>
            <p>1623.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:10328:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10328:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Marcus Antonius de Dominis,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Spalatto,</hi> declareth the cauſe why he left <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MOſt excellently, as he doth all other things, hath the holy <hi>Ghoſt</hi> by the mouth of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul,</hi> numbred vp amongſt the works of the fleſh, <hi>contentions, emulations, anger, quarrels, diſcentions,</hi> and<note place="margin">Gal. 5. 20.</note> 
               <hi>ſects;</hi> for I haue had too much triall in my ſelfe of the vnhappy fruit of this vnluckie tree; And now hauing receiued a potion of Diuine grace for my recouery, muſt vomit out that filthineſſe, which before through the ſickneſſe of my minde, and corruption of my taſte, I had greedily deuoured: which that I might the more ſafely and ſpeedily performe, and correct my ſelfe in publicke before all the world, and condemne to the pit of hell my infinite errours ſprung from the wicked intention of my firſt going <hi>into England;</hi> I haue taken that good counſell, firſt to leaue the Schoole of errours, lyes, and hereſies: and then of mine owne free will to returne to the holy <hi>Romane Church,</hi> the one, and onely piller and excellent ground of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke truth, and the Mother of all Catholickes, from whom I had moſt wickedly departed. Firſt, therefore I will proſecute this my correction, condemnation, and deteſtation of my errours, and afterwards I will declare the other cauſes why I left <hi>England,</hi> and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hereticall Countries whatſoeuer, and returned to the holy Catholick Romane Church.</p>
            <p>2 It is the moſt auncient diſeaſe of our corrupt hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature deſcended from our firſt Father vnto all his poſterity, that when we fall into any errour, or ſlide into any vice, we doe either finde out filthy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes
<pb facs="tcp:10328:3"/> (as <hi>the woman which thou gaueſt me to be my fellow</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deu 3. 2.</note> 
               <hi>companion, gaue me of the tree, and I did eate</hi>) or elſe we defend our faults, and endeuour to couer them with a counterfait cloake of Iuſtice, and honeſty: and I confeſſe that this was my caſe, for which I am very ſorrie. The diſeaſe of my minde (in which before my departure from the <hi>Romane Church</hi> I languiſhed) was, that contrary to the wholeſome counſell of the wiſe man, I truſted too much to mine owne prudence, and<note place="margin">Pro. 3. 5.</note> out of the confidence of my owne wit being no body, I would giue very raſh iudgement in matters of faith, vnto which alſo was ioyned a certaine frenzie of anger. Not that, which ſome weake Schollers at my going out of <hi>England</hi> imputed vnto me, becauſe I was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied vaine pretended dignities; but it proceeded alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether out of mine owne vnreaſonable impatience, by taking in euill part to be made ſubiect to others of whom I did vndeſeruedly complaine in my booke of the cauſe of my departing. Theſe things draue me vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the quicke ſands and ſhallowes; theſe caſt me vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Rockes; theſe ſharpened my wit to inuent pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiferous cogitations; theſe made me vainely to pittie the errours of the <hi>Romane Church,</hi> thereby to excuſe my departure from it; theſe made me to tranſcend all limits. And that I might ſeeme to haue done well in leauing the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and auoide by ſome meanes the brand of impudencie, raſhneſſe, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; in defence of my departure, I ſet forth firſt an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of mine intent, and afterwards certaine vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes, and little bookes, into which I thruſt what the Art of counterfaiting, and diſſimulation had inuented, and aduice of the fleſh ſuggeſted. And ſo as long as the inward diſeaſe increaſed, and the ſpurres of anger pricked my exulcerated minde; the itching of my
<pb facs="tcp:10328:3"/> tongue and pen, brake forth into madneſſe: and now my vnderſtanding being darkened, many things which the Enemies of the Apoſtolicall ſea (tranſported with hereſie) did beleeue, affirme, and profeſſe; ſeemed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me credible and ſome-things alſo true, as long as I did not try the Doctrine in controuerſie by the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of true Diuinity, nor perfectly diſcuſſe them: for at that time I had neither finiſhed, nor yet begun ſome of the parts of the <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Common-wealth,</hi> in which I had purpoſed to treat of the decrees, and rules of faith, howſoeuer in the booke of my intent of leauing the <hi>Romane Church,</hi> I affirmed that I had them all ready for the Preſſe; and being thus blinded, and relying raſhly more vpon the falſe accuſations of the heretickes, then vpon the truth of the Catholick faith; I wrote the little bookes of the <hi>intent of my depaerture,</hi> from the <hi>Romane Church,</hi> and the <hi>Rockes of Chriſtian ſhipwracke,</hi> and a certaine <hi>Sermon</hi> ſtuffed with errours and hereſie; and out of my then conceiued hatred, which for the moſt part I bare to the holy <hi>Romane Church,</hi> the Apoſtolicall ſea, and the Pope; I affirmed theſe things, and many more to be true, which before I writ them, I knew to be falſe, and hereticall; and afterwards in ſome part corrected them, and with my whole heart deteſted them, euen when I writ them; and now alſo I abhorre and deteſt theſe little bookes, becauſe they containe manifeſt hereſies againſt Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke truthes, and are repugnant to ſound Doctrine; that is to ſay, to the Doctrine which the holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Romane Church doth, and hath alwayes main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; againſt which Doctrine whatſoeuer I haue ſpoken, or written, that I doe wholy condemne, and deteſt; and by the grace of <hi>God</hi> I will more amply, and largely condemne, and deteſt it, in the confutation of
<pb facs="tcp:10328:4"/> my bookes of <hi>the Eccleſiaſticall Common-wealth,</hi> and of the other bookes, which I haue written: for I doe wholly ſubmit my ſelfe, and all my bookes to the moſt holy iudgement, and cenſure of the holy Romane, and Apoſtolicke ſea, the chiefe of all Churches whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer.</p>
            <p>3 In the meane ſpace, it is neceſſary in this my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and truly ſound determination, to deteſt that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of my <hi>vnhappy departing</hi> from the <hi>Romane</hi> Church, and the <hi>infamous Rockes,</hi> ſhipwracks chiefly to my ſelfe and heretiques, and not of Catholicks, and alſo that <hi>Sermon.</hi> Neither will I be aſhamed by pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling off my garments, which I had forged to my ſelfe, to lay open my nakedneſſe, becauſe I haue not beene aſhamed againſt all right and honeſty, to breake forth into vaine lyes, manifeſt ſlaunders, and ſilthy hereſies. The ſtinging and venome of the Scorpion is cured by the bruiſing of the ſame Scorpion which pricked: and if the voluntary contrition, and bruiſing of my ſelfe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diaſcor. lib. cap.</hi> 44.</note> may heale the venomous wounds of others (if any be wounded by me) I will eſteeme this my bruiſing, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, and mortification moſt happy. Let the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Catholicke Church, and of the Apoſtolicall ſea, remaine vnmoueable, although it be with the loſſe of whatſoeuer I haue in this life, ſeeing I haue ſought to diminiſh it: for at laſt, that loſſe muſt needs before God be glorious to me alſo: Wherefore I doe firſt confeſſe, and truly and ſincerely out of my owne conſcience, doe giue teſtimony, that I did not write the <hi>intent of my departing</hi> from the Romane Church, and the <hi>Rockes</hi> and the <hi>Sermon</hi> out of ſincerity of heart, or out of a good conſcience, or faith not fained: but that I might couer with ſome excuſe my ſhamefull depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and be more gratefull and acceptable to hereticks,
<pb facs="tcp:10328:4"/> to whom (wretch that I was) I ranne in haſt, and with whom I familiarly conuerſed. The ten yeares labour which in the booke of the <hi>intent of my departing</hi> I boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of, were not ſpent in mature deliberations, graue and aduiſed Counſels, or other diſcreete diſcuſſions of the truth: but contrariwiſe miſpent, in vaine, vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and malicious purpoſes, and preparations, how I might boldly vent and put in practiſe my hereticall lyes and inuentions, thereby to ſatisfie my malitious anger: inſomuch, as my vocation to doe it, was not a Diuine vocation, but a deuilliſh ſuggeſtion, ſtirred vp in me not by the holy <hi>Ghoſt,</hi> but by a wicked ſpirit, a ſpirit of giddines worſe then was that of <hi>Saules.</hi> And I do not doubt to attribute my returne back againe, to a true Diuine vocation; the <hi>holy</hi> Ghoſt calling me to returne vnto my Mother, the Catholicke <hi>Romane Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4 I ſaid that the manners of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> did cauſe mee alwayes to abhorre it. This I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to haue bin wickedly ſpoken, for neither then, nor yet is wanting in <hi>Rome</hi> very many notable exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of piety, and all Chriſtian vertues, which may both delight, and incite religious mindes to further deuotion. I ſaid that by forbidding the reading of bookes written againſt the Doctrine of <hi>Rome,</hi> there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe ſome euill ſuſpitions, which gaue credit to the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of hereticks, and made men beleeue that there is ſome thing in them ſecretly, which Catholicks are not able to anſwere. This I confeſſe to haue beene iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſpoken of me againſt the Catholicke faith, who found in the bookes of hereticks, falſe, hereticall, ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous, and peſtiferous Doctrine; from the reading whereof the faithfull are to be kept, leaſt it infect their ſoules. Neither is it a thing befitting priuate men to
<pb facs="tcp:10328:5"/> read ſuch bookes, but the iudgement in matters of ſuch alwayes did, and now doth belong vnto the Shepheards, who finding venomous Paſtures, ſhould remoue their ſheepe as farre from them as they can: Moreouer, the arguments of hereticks are deceitfull, Sophiſticall, and eaſie to be anſwered. I ſaid that the Doctrine of thoſe who oppoſed themſelues againſt the <hi>Romane Church,</hi> did either nothing, or little differ from the Doctrine of the auncient Church: and this is falſe: for the opinions wherein they differ from Catholicks, are wholly differing from the Doctrine of the auncient Church; and nothing can more connince them, then the authority of the auncient Church, from which they by their nouelties haue ſo farre departed, that worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for this reſpect they are condemned for hereticks, by the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> It is therefore deteſtable, and I deteſt that which I ſaid, that their Doctrines were therefore condemned onely by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe theſe things they ſaid, were repugnant vnto the ſenſuality, and corrupt manners of the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi> I ſaid alſo, that at <hi>Rome</hi> they coyned new ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of faith by maine force. And this I ſaid truly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my conſcience, for I neuer obſerued it at any time, and I certainely know, that it cannot be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by any man. For the declarations and explications made by holy Church touching articles and myſteries of faith (collected out of Diuine Scriptures, and tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Fathers, and out of the very rules of faith) cannot any wayes be termed new coyning of articles. Moreouer, I endeauoured to take away the title of <hi>Catholicke</hi> and <hi>vntuerſall,</hi> from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in which I erred very much; for by the <hi>Catholicke Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Church,</hi> is vnderſtood not onely that ſpeciall and perticular Church which is at <hi>Rome,</hi> but alſo the whole
<pb facs="tcp:10328:5"/> multitude and company of all the Churches adhearing vnto the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in the vnity of faith, and in obedience to the Pope in what place ſoeuer they be, yea in the vtmoſt confines of the earth. And it is moſt true, and was approued by me both by word of mouth (as <hi>England</hi> it ſelfe may witneſſe) and by writing (in my Treatiſes of the <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> Common-wealth, in that part which I heare is lately ſet forth in <hi>Germany</hi>) that no Church is <hi>Catholicke</hi> but the <hi>Romane,</hi> and ſuch as are vnited vnto her. For all other congregations of Chriſtians being ſtayned with hereſies, and deuided and ſeperated by Schiſme from the <hi>Romane</hi> Church are, and be excluded from the Catholicke, vniuerſall and true Church of Chriſt: and being as it were blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, together with their blinde Guides doe ruſh, and runne headlong into the bottomleſſe pit of perdition, which I wickedly affirmed of the <hi>Romanes</hi> to their great wrong: For from the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> at all times, a moſt glorious light of pure and incorrupted faith came forth, and doth at this preſent lighten all other Churches of Chriſt whatſoeuer. But I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that in the preface of the bookes of the <hi>Chriſtian Common-wealth,</hi> among other things I vſed ſome words, in which I ſeeme to put and place in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Church, all them who haue receiued Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme in the name of the Bleſſed <hi>Trinity,</hi> and in ſo ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, althought the words ſound euill, and make the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall Churches true and ſound members of the true Catholicke Church, which is moſt falſe and hereticall; yet my meaning was, vtterly to exclude the <hi>Arrian, Neſtorian,</hi> and <hi>Eutichian</hi> hereſies, and all hereticall Churches condemned in former times, and to retaine them onely that were <hi>Orthodoxall:</hi> But herein I was deceiued in that I eſteemed, that there were many
<pb facs="tcp:10328:6"/> more Orthodoxall Churches then are, for I erroniouſly beleeued, that many Churches which are infected with the hereſies of theſe later Times, and deuided by Schiſme, did appertaine vnto the <hi>Catholicke Church,</hi> which although it be called <hi>Catholicke,</hi> for that it is <hi>vniuerſall;</hi> yet <hi>vniuerſality</hi> doth not comprehend any but thoſe that be Orthodoxall, and true beleeuing, and dilated ouer all the world, and continuing in the Catholicke vnity with the <hi>Romane.</hi> For the vniuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the <hi>Romane Church,</hi> conſiſteth not onely in the perpetuall, and neuer interrupted or to be interrupted continuance and firmeneſſe of faith, but is alſo vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall; becauſe her <hi>Identicall,</hi> or ſelfe ſame faith and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne gouernement, hath beene dilated and ſpread ouer all places, and into Nations after the comming of Chriſt; for which reſpect euen in theſe later times and ages, it is to be called <hi>Catholicke,</hi> no leſſe then it was in the times of the auncient Fathers; ſeeing that the faith of the <hi>Romane Church</hi> is dilated in theſe our times into the fartheſt, and moſt vaſt or remote Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Eaſt, and Weſt, and euen to the vttermoſt confines of the earth. So that her children trauelling too and fro, from the riſing of the Sunne vnto the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thereof, profeſſing the faith of Chriſt, and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring cleane ſacrifices, doe eſpecially at this time fulfill, that which our Lord ſpake by the mouth of <hi>Malachie,</hi> ſaying, chap. 1. ver. 11. <hi>From the riſing of the Sunne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the goinng downe thereof, great is my name amongst the Gentiles, and in euery place it is ſanctified, and a pure oblation is offered vnto my name.</hi> Neither was it a leſſe iniury and ſlaunder, when I ſaid, that I clearly ſaw innumerable nouelties &amp; errors in the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> which nouelties &amp; errors I doe neither ſee, nor yet did euer ſee: and I acknowledge and confeſſe that it was
<pb facs="tcp:10328:6"/> moſt falſe, that at <hi>Rome</hi> there was then, or now are any errours, by which any deſtruction of ſoules may follow, or the peace of the Church be diſturbed, or publique ſcandalls committed: For in truth all the peace &amp; all the tranquility of the Catholique Church, and the eternall ſaluation of Soules, after <hi>God</hi> is to be attributed to the care and trauell of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> I ſaid that the mightier Biſhops vnder the <hi>Pope</hi> were Biſhops onely in name, and this ſaying con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth in it both falſhood and wrong, and therefore I doe condemne it, as euill ſpoken, for they be true and lawfull Biſhops, made by lawfull ordination. I ſaid that the others who were not great men and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in temporall things, had loſt the proper dignity, and power of Biſhops; and this truly is a ſlaunder, for the <hi>Hierarchicall</hi> ſubordination, was alwayes neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in the Church: much more I condemne as an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie thoſe words where I ſaid, that vnder the <hi>Pope</hi> was no more a true Church; for as I ſaid and ſeriouſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed before, onely the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with her ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents, is the true Church of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and the others are not Churches. And in fewe words, to comprehend much, I perceiued that in my former intention I chiefly indeauoured to weaken the ſupremacie of the <hi>Pope,</hi> and in ſo doing, I confeſſe that I haue ſpoken againſt the faith of the whole <hi>Catholique Church,</hi> and haue er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red greeuouſly. For it is euident both by the very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution in the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> and by the Apoſtolicke tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the dcfinitions of holy Synods, and generall Councels, and very many decrees of the <hi>Pope,</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the common teſtimony of the Fathers and Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Hiſtories, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> was inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted chiefe head of the whole Church immediatly by <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord as a ſingular Oracle, vnto whom both
<pb facs="tcp:10328:7"/> the Eaſt and Weſt Churches in all doubts of Faith, ſhould haue recourſe for inſtructions, definitions, and other ſound doctrine in matters of Faith, as vnto a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter giuen them from heauen, who by his office ſhould teach the Church. And any one that is but meanly read, may eaſily finde out very many examples, where the <hi>Popes of Rome</hi> eſtabliſhed, remooued, corrected, taught, condemned, abſolued, depoſed, reſtored, and reprehended, according to ther office, euen the <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs</hi> and <hi>Prymats</hi> of the Eaſt; And thus reprehended, they humbly heard, and ſimply obayed the <hi>Popes</hi> without reſiſtance, or repugnance. And to be ſhort, it is manifeſt by the confeſſion of the whole Church, that all the ſpirit of <hi>Chriſt</hi> (for ſo much as doth belong vnto the deciſion of matters of faith) doth reſt vpon one Supreame viſible head of the Church, which is onely the <hi>Pope</hi> and chiefe Biſhop, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſour.</p>
            <p>5 I doe ingenuouſly confeſſe, that the booke which I called <hi>The Rockes of Chriſtian ſhipwracke,</hi> did much diſpleaſe me, preſently after it was ſet forth; for I wrote it in haſt without either ſtudy, or examining what I did. The intent which I had in writing of it, was onely to flatter &amp; allure the Engliſh by all meanes poſſible to conceiue a good opinion of me at my firſt comming, and ſo I had no regard whither that I writ and printed were true or no: But my deſire was to ſay that which might pleaſe the Enemies of the Catholicke Church, and eſpecially the ignorant common people. And when the doctrine contained in this little booke, was by the King and ſome of the Nobility objected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me (at my preparing to depart from <hi>England</hi>) I did euen then in expreſſe words deteſt it; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards prepared my ſelfe with all my force to reſiſt the greater part of the hereſies which were in it: All which
<pb facs="tcp:10328:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> hereſies I doe now againe reject, deteſt, and abhorre; and they are theſe: That the <hi>Pope of Rome</hi> is not the Vicar of Chriſt vpon earth, nor viſible head of the whole viſible Church of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> That hee hath no power in temporall thinges; That an implicit faith profiteth nothing, but much hurteth the faithfull: That the Excommunications of the Law are vaine threats: That the precepts of the Church binde not vpon paine of mortall ſinne: That the vnity of the Church is not to be ſought for from one onely viſible head: That the <hi>Pope</hi> is a deadly Enemy of vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall Church: That the <hi>Maſſe</hi> is not a true ſacrifice: That the Ceremonies of the Maſſe are Apiſh toyes: That there is no Tranſubſtantiation: That Auricular confeſſion with abſolution is not a true Sacrament: That there is no Purgatory: That Satisfaction after the fault forgiuen, is not neceſſary for the remiſſion of the puniſhment: That there be no Indulgences but of things enjoyned for penance. That Saints are not to be prayed vnto: That the worſhip of Images and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques are not lawfull: That there is no merrit of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life by workes. Theſe and the like errours and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt hereſies, not ſo much mine, or newly inuented by me, as by the olde and new hereticks, whoſe fancies and madneſſe haue beene from time to time by the Church in generall Counſels condemned: for they are miſerable <hi>Rockes,</hi> vnto which if any approach, they are aſſured to ſuffer a lamentable ſhipwracke of faith and eternall ſaluation: And therefore I departed from them as farre as I might, and leaſt I ſhould be vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by them in <hi>England,</hi> it was neceſſary for me to depart from thence, and to returne to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> the true port of Catholickes, with the which Church I reject, deteſt, and accurſe all the afore ſaid
<pb facs="tcp:10328:8"/> errours, and all others opinions whatſoeuer (if there be any more in thoſe bookes) which doe not agree with the faith expreſſed in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and in the ſacred Counſels, eſpecially in the Counſell of Trent: and I doe conſtantly affirme and embrace the contrary verities, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Pope</hi> is by the inſtitution of <hi>Chriſt</hi> his Vicar vpon earth, and the viſible head of the whole militant Church (which hath alwayes beene viſible) with full power receiued from <hi>God;</hi> to rule and gouerne her: That he hath alſo indirect power in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall matters, for the better aduancement of ſpiritual. That an implicit faith is profitable, and many times ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, <hi>viz.</hi> when the explicit faith of ſome articles is not required vnder penalty: That the excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions according to the Law, or <hi>de facto</hi> pronounced, are of force, and ought to be feared, as brought into the Church with great reaſon, and by lawfull authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: that the <hi>Pope</hi> may excommunicate the faithfull whereſoeuer they are: That the precepts of the Church binde vnder paine of mortall ſinne: That the vnity of the Church dependeth chiefely of one onely viſible head of the ſame Church: That the <hi>Pope</hi> is the true and lawfull Paſtor of the whole Church, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto his obligation is zealous of the good of Chriſts flocke, by daily thirſting after, and moſt care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully procuring their eternall ſaluation: That in the Maſſe is offered, a true, proper, and propitiatory ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice vnto God: That the ceremonies of the Maſſe inſtituted by the holy Fathers, and Paſtors of the Church (by the inſpiration of the holy Ghoſt) are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, myſticall, profitable, and ought to be obſerued and kept: That in the Sacrament of the Alter, there is tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnbſtantiation, that is to ſay, a conuerſion of all the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of bread into the body, and of wine into the
<pb facs="tcp:10328:8"/> blood of our Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> That in the ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall abſolution which the Prieſt vſeth in abſoluting from ſins, is exerciſed the true and proper power of binding, &amp; looſing ſins, which our <hi>Lord</hi> hath deliuered or giuen to the Miniſters of his Sacraments in the Church: That there is a Purgatory after that manner and ſort which the holy <hi>Romane</hi> and Apoſtolicke Church doth affirme it to be: That ſatisfaction is of great power, after the fault remitted for the remiſſion of the puniſhment alſo: That the vſe of Indulgences in the Catholicke Church (vnto whom Chriſt hath giuen authority to beſtowe them) is very auncient, very profitable, and approued by the authority of holy Councels: That we may not onely lawfully pray vnto Saints, but alſo that it is a good and profitable thing to flye for helpe vnto their prayers, and ayde: That the worſhip of Images and Reliques, is good, lawfull, and profitable, and cannot be rejected without the blot of hereſie: That the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of eternall life dependeth vpon good workes; Alſo I often times loathed and deſpiſed the later generall Councels (which be of high authority in the Church) eſpecially the Councels of <hi>Florence</hi> and <hi>Trent,</hi> and ſometimes that of <hi>Conſtance.</hi> And by my meanes it came to paſſe, that a certaine Hiſtory of the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> was publiſhed, whereof I could haue no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine knowledge, for that it was iuſtly ſuſpected of forgerie; and in theſe things alſo I confeſſe that I haue maliciouſly erred, and now affirme that all the moſt wholſome decrees of theſe Councels are worthy of credit, and ought to be embraced.</p>
            <p>6 In a certaine Sermon of mine on the firſt Sonday of Aduent, made at <hi>London</hi> in the Italian tongue, and printed, I publiſhed almoſt the ſame errours, which I repeated after in the booke of the <hi>Rockes,</hi> all which I
<pb facs="tcp:10328:9"/> doe now deepely deteſt. In that Sermon I faigned a certaine darke night of Popiſh errours, and of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> when in very deede in the onely Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and in the Churches connexed vnto her, is a true and cleare Sunne-ſhining day, and out of her (eſpecially in <hi>England</hi>) there is a perpetuall night, and moſt obſcure darkneſſe. The light of truth, and the true and right vnderſtanding of the Scriptures, which is in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> driueth farre from her the miſtes of all theſe errours, wherewith wretched <hi>England</hi> being ouer-clowded, walketh, as a blinde man groping for the wall at mid-day. I ſaid in the ſame Sermon, and I repeated the ſame in the little booke of the <hi>Rockes,</hi> that <hi>Peter</hi> was neuer at <hi>Rome,</hi> yet notwithſtanding I know that this is a groſſe and an ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantlye, and therefore I doe ingenuouſly confeſſe, that it ought to be rejected of all men. I made the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> equall in founding and ruling the Church; when yet euen out of the very Goſpels, and Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall tradition, the Supremacie of <hi>Peter</hi> (aboue them) is apparant. I ſaid that the Biſhops ſucceeded the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles</hi> with equall power, and that they were Biſhops of the vniuerſall Church in groſſe, when as they are but Paſtors of perticular Churches, in their ſole particular cares or charges: the generall Primacie belonging vnto him who ſucceeded <hi>Peter,</hi> which is the <hi>Pope.</hi> I ſaid that holy water, graynes, croſſes, holy Images, the Popes or Biſhops benediction, Stations, habites, girdles, belts, the viſitations of Churches Altars, Beades, Proceſſions, and the like, were meere toyes; when yet it is certaine, that the vſe of almoſt all theſe things is well approued, and very auncient in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church, and ought to be preſerued together with the vſe of other things of later times added, as
<pb facs="tcp:10328:9"/> prouokements to piety aad deuotion. I affirmed that there were onely two Sacraments, Baptiſme and the Supper, when yet the Catholicke Church illuminated by the holy Ghoſt plainely teacheth and defineth, that there are ſeuen true Sacraments: All which, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer other hereſies condemned by the Catholicke <hi>Romane Church,</hi> I alſo condemne, and the things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to them being defined by the ſame, I alſo with a firme faith beleeue, holde, and profeſſe. For moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it is, that in the decrees of the holy <hi>Romane Church,</hi> reaſon is not ſeperated from authority, and that the Doctrine of the Schoolemen is altogether con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant vnto the ſence of the holy Fathers, eſpecially in articles of faith. I alſo confeſſe that I did vndeſeruedly in theſe little Pamphlets complaine of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> as if ſhe had vſurped other mens rights; for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſhe preſerue by her lawfull authority ouer them, the Biſhops, and Archbiſhops in their duties, there would preſently follow a generall violation of her lawes by them: And the Church is then very happy, when all her perticular Paſtors vnder the moſt vigilant and higheſt Paſtor, doe readily receiue and execute both reformation in manners, and the cuſtody of ſound and ſincere Doctrine, from him who hath the ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne authority. And verily, except the benigne and paternall care of the holy Inquiſition, had watched ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly ouer our Lords flocke, the ſcabbed cattell ſhould not receiue any cure, but the filthy Canker would daily encreaſe. The ordinary Armour of that Tribunall, is found Doctrine, and charitable inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and not thoſe inſtruments which (out of a minde corrupted with malice) in my Pamphlets I haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agerated by lyes and ſlaunders, and yet ſometimes when rotten vlcers cannot be cured with gentle medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines,
<pb facs="tcp:10328:10"/> it is both fit and neceſſary that the Phyſitians ſhould vſe more forceable remedies.</p>
            <p>7 But when the inward burning of the infirmities of my minde was alayed almoſt by a miracle about the beginning of the Popedome of the moſt holy <hi>Gregory</hi> the 15. (whoſe rare piety, ſingular prudence, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall holineſſe of life was ſuch, as that I doe not doubt but that it was cauſe of his aduancement to that high dignity) the holy Ghoſt illuminating me with a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine diuine light, my minde began to thinke vpon wholſome courſes, And then the dangers into which I had caſt my ſoule, began alſo euery day more clearely to muſter themſelues in troupes before me, and I did wonder how I had fallen into ſo great madneſſe and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, as to ioyne my ſelfe vnto them who were here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and abſolute and manifeſt Schiſmaticks. In olde time ſo great was the craſt of a fewe <hi>Arians</hi> in the Councell of <hi>Arminium,</hi> that by a cunning ſleight they almoſt drew all the Catholicks to ſeeme <hi>Arians:</hi> And then ſaith our S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Hierome</hi> againſt the Luciferians) all the world lamented, and wondred how it became in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with Araniſme: But (with griefe I ſpeake it) ſo it happened vnto me, and much worſe; and I would wonder and mourne to ſee my ſelfe an heretick among hereticks, and a Schiſmatick with Schiſmaticks. But heerein let not the Engliſh complaine that I wrong them: but rather let them plainely know, that I haue done well, and as I ought to doe, in departing from them, and returning vnto my mother the holy woman-Church. And as for the laying open of their here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and Schiſme, I am compelled to doe it, for that it is not fit for mee to be poyſoned any longer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
            <p>8 Concerning Religion, there are in <hi>England</hi> ſundry
<pb facs="tcp:10328:10"/> Sects: There are Puritanes that is the rigid Caluiniſts; There are ſome milder, who call themſelues onely Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and reformed: There are Anabaptiſts who are alſo deuided into diuers Sects: There wanteth not Arians, nor Photinians, and ſuch a like miſh-maſh of wicked people, who though they be not permitted to profeſſe their errours publiquely, yet are they not caſt forth of their Church nor puniſhed, but tollerated whileſt they publiſh their poyſon. Moreouer, that the Anabaptiſts ſwarme with hereſies, none but the Anna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſt himſelfe will denie it, yet they haue their free meetings in <hi>England,</hi> and the Kings <hi>Mateſtie</hi> one day tolde me, that lately at <hi>London</hi> a woman did in an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> both make a publicke Sermon, and alſo adminiſter their ſuppoſed Sacraments. The hereſies of the <hi>Puritanes</hi> are well knowne, which are theſe: That there is no free will: That <hi>God</hi> is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of ſinne: That <hi>God</hi> for his pleafure condemneth many without cauſe: That <hi>Chriſt</hi> did not dye for all men: That <hi>Chriſt</hi> did ſuſtaine the paines of the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: That Infants dying after Baptiſme, may be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, &amp;c. The milder <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> although they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour by all meanes to free themſelues (for as much as concerneth their opinions) from hereſie, for that they ſeeme neither wholly to follow <hi>Luther</hi> nor <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine:</hi> but the pure Doctrine of the Engliſh Church which they call reformed; yet can they not be free from the hereſie both of the <hi>Puritanes,</hi> and <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> for that they communicate with them without ſcruple; and if any <hi>Puritane</hi> or <hi>Anabaptiſt</hi> come to their Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall aſſemblies, they neither auoyde, nor exclude him. And the <hi>Puritane</hi> Miniſters (who are almoſt all wholly infected with all hereſies, or at leaſt with the hereſies of <hi>Caluine</hi>) doe adminiſter the very Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb facs="tcp:10328:11"/> of this falſe Engliſh Church. And if that <hi>Acatius</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> becauſe he communicated with <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus Moggus</hi> an hereticke of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> if all the Eaſt becauſe it perſiſted in the communion of <hi>Acatius,</hi> was ſeperated by a long enduring curſe from the Weſt, how much more are all the <hi>Engliſh Proteſtants</hi> to be accounted hereticks, for that they doe commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate continually with hereticks, and doe neither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne them, nor ſeperate themſelues from them, but admit them euen when they communicate with them in diuine things? Doth not the deformed Engliſh Church publickly and openly profeſſe a communion and Eccleſiaſticall league with <hi>Geneua</hi> the mother of the <hi>Puritanes,</hi> and other outlandiſh Sects infected with Caluinian poyſon? In the Royall Citie of <hi>London</hi> by publicke leaue of the King, are not the Churches of the <hi>French, Dutch,</hi> and <hi>Italian</hi> Caluiniſts open, and eſteemed moſt louing Siſters of the Engliſh Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, although they deteſt the Engliſh doctrine, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and rites, and be the chiefeſt fauourers, and promoters of Puritaniſme in <hi>England:</hi> And alſo the Engliſh Synagogue as much (as in her lyeth) is moſt ready to communicate with the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> being pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted with the filthy dregges of many hereſies, and earneſtly laboureth that theſe Monſters may growe vp together with her into one <hi>Hydra,</hi> that there may be made an vnion of all the reformed Churches as they call them; and yet haue no care, nor take any paynes to purge their faith, and doctrine, and pull vp their he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies; although the <hi>Lutherans</hi> hate the Sacramentaries worſe then <hi>the dogge doth the Snake.</hi> Of the other Engliſh hereſies about Faith, and Workes, and Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, about the bleſſed Sacrament, and priuate Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, about Merits, and inuocation of Saints, the vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb facs="tcp:10328:11"/> of holy Images, holy Ceremonies, the ſoules of the departed, and the like, which theſe hereticks con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne in their hereticall ſpirit, and which I alſo in their companies with the ſame ſpirit of hereſie in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time haue in ſome part condemned, it is not now my intent to ſpeake much, by and by I will giue them a touch according to the nature of this place: at ſome other time I will ſpeake more largely of them, now I come to ſpeake of their Schiſme.</p>
            <p>I haue no doubt at all, but that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Sect, which the ſtayned <hi>Engliſh</hi> call the reformed Church, is much more deuided and ſeperated from the true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Church: then Brittany it ſelfe is deuided from the reſt of the world. They themſelues will willingly confeſſe, and it is a thing of it ſelfe moſt manifeſt, that they are wholy deuided &amp; ſeperated from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and from all the Churches which are ſubiect vnto her, and liue in community with her. And ſeeing that the <hi>Romane Church</hi> with thoſe which adheare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her, is according to Catholicke faith, truly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly the Catholicke Church of Chriſt: Doth it not then neceſſarily follow, that the Engliſh congregation which they call a Church, is altogether ſeperated from the true Catholicke Church? and conſequently neither to be the body of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> nor the houſe of <hi>God,</hi> nor ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely a Church? which thing as ſoone as I plainely vnderſtood, I could not ſtay any longer in it. But they will ſay it appeareth now vnto thee ſo: who yet in thy bookes of <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Common-wealth</hi> haſt called <hi>Rome Babylon,</hi> who haſt denied that there was any Church in <hi>Rome,</hi> and alſo haſt taught vs that it was properly a Schiſmaticall Church: But that which thou fayeſt of our Church is not manifeſt vnto vs: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will endeauour that it may be alſo manifeſt vnto
<pb facs="tcp:10328:12"/> the Engliſh. They know very well that I am not <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras,</hi> whoſe onely authority amongſt his Schollers was accepted for proofe, wherefore they ſhould not haue beene moued at theſe things I ſpake, ſeeing they were but have aſtertions, and for this cauſe my words euen yet are vaine; for when I bring forth the proofes and examples they are without force and ground. The reaſon whereupon ſgrounded my poſition of <hi>Rome</hi> to be <hi>Babtlon</hi> was, becauſe the Propheſie in the 18. of the <hi>Apocalips</hi> could not be interpreted of <hi>Rome,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it receiued the Chriſtian faith, and whilſt it was the habitation of the Gentiles: But this reaſon is of no force; for ſuppoſe that it were true, yet it doth not follow that <hi>Rome</hi> being now Chriſtian ſhould be that <hi>Babtlon</hi> ſpoken of in the <hi>Apocalips;</hi> for it is the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of many Catholicke Interpreters, that in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of Antichriſt, the Ethnick Idolaters, and the Enemies of the Chriſtian name ſhall (perhaps) ſubdue it, and of ſuch that propheſie (not yet fulfilled) may be fitly verified, yet in ſuch ſort, as the faith of the Catholicke Church may continue ſafe and found: Whereby now you ſee that my applying it to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>Rome,</hi> is but a meere calumniation; for I know that Chriſtian <hi>Rome</hi> is not <hi>Babylon,</hi> neither can it be ſo called without great iniurie, and God forbid that by this Proheſie, we ſhould vnderſtand the ſame <hi>Romane Church,</hi> which is the Mother, and the head of all, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to haue beene, or hereafter to become <hi>Babylon;</hi> for thoſe things which are ſpoken of the Citie, are not to be tranſferred vnto the Church. I denied that there is a Church at <hi>Rome,</hi> but I did not proue it; therefore that negation muſt be layed vp amongſt my euill ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, reproaches, and hereſies, and conuincing my ſelfe within my ſelfe being ouercome by reaſon euen in
<pb facs="tcp:10328:12"/> the ſame Treatiſes, I conſtantly affirmed, that the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Church</hi> with her adherents was the only Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and now I doe moſt earneſtly profeſſe and affirme it. I ſaid it made a Schiſme, when I had not yet exact conſideration what a Schiſme was; and in this I erred groſly, this being a manifeſt falſehood, and the proofe which I brought in confirmation is of no force: For he who is lawfully appointed head of a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and calleth and publiſheth himſelfe for head of the ſame body, doth not ſeperate himſelfe from the body, neither caſteth away the body from him, but ioyneth himſelfe vnto the body, which hath no coherence with a Schiſme: yet I will handle this matter more at large in the correction of that worke. Now I proceede to declare how it is euident to me, that the Engliſh Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and much more all the other Sectaries of our age, are truly and properly Schiſmaticks, becauſe they haue ſeperated themſelues without any lawfull cauſe from the true Church of Chriſt, which is the Catholick Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Church, and her adherents.</p>
            <p>10 There can be onely two cauſes of a lawfull ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, why one, or more Churches of <hi>Chriſt</hi> (and yet not commit Schiſme) ſhould abandon one or more o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Churches from their communion: The one is he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, and the other is Schiſme it ſelfe. This is well knowne vnto all the faithfull, that the hereticall Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches which are incorrigible, are to be auoyded by Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes, and that with ſuch, they ought not to haue any Eccleſiaſticall communion. I enquired often times of the Engliſh, why they ſeperated themſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the church of <hi>Rome</hi> &amp; her adherents, whither for any here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie? And truly not none of them could either by words or writing, ſhew me that the <hi>Romane Catholicks</hi> either of our time, or in the time of our aunceſtors in their
<pb facs="tcp:10328:13"/> generall publi ke profeſſion were at any time ſtayned with any hereſie. The Kings <hi>Maieſtie</hi> himſelfe of great <hi>Eritanie,</hi> granted to me publickly, and plainely, and ſo did the wiſer ſort of their Miniſters of all ſorts, and not a fewe of their learned men, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> did not erre in fundamentall poynts of Faith; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is not hereticall, if we will take but that which they graunt. Perhaps they will ſay the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth not erre in fundamentall poynts of faith (which thing I alſo ſeemed to teach, eſpecially in the cauſes of my departing, and in the Sermon I preached at <hi>London</hi>) yet they erre, and are fallen into hereſie in other articles of faith, which be not fundamentall: But firſt, I know not what article it may be of true faith, which is not fundamentall; for neither could I vnderſtand, nor they explicate vnto me, how there may be ſuch a diſtinction made or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, that ſome be fundamentall and ſome not: I haue alwayes thought, that all and the ſole articles which are truly articles of faith were fundamentall, yet I errred when I excluded many true articles from the fundamentall; which being true, were alſo fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall articles, and without hereſie, could not be denied: although they be not of thoſe principall articles of the Trinity, incarnation, neceſſity of grace, Baptiſme in the name of the Trinity, &amp;c. ſuch as are the Sacraments, iuſtification, neceſſity of workes, merrits, indulgences, and the reſt, which I haue before rehearſed, as already limitted in the Church, becauſe thoſe things relye no leſſe vpon the reuelation of <hi>God</hi> then the former, and for that cauſe appertaine no leſſe vnto faith then thoſe. For he that thinketh <hi>God</hi> to be a deceiuer in any one article whatſoeuer it be muſt of neceſſity alſo acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him to be a deceiuer in all the reſt. Then I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired
<pb facs="tcp:10328:13"/> often times of them who dealt ſeriouſly in the buſineſſe, to ſhew ſome article of faith, in which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> thought, &amp; taught erroniouſly. They vſe to bring the article of Tranſubſtantion of the bread into the body of Chriſt, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which they gather (as they think) ſome hereſies, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath not a true body, but a phantaſticall, if that in the leaſt crum of the bread we put that whole body, ſo that a body ſhould not be a body. Item, that Chriſt is not in heauen, if he be vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Altar on earth, which is contrary to the article of the aſcenſion of our <hi>Lord.</hi> Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that Chriſt is not borne of the virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> if that we do make him of bread. In theſe men it is moſt true, that which S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith vpon the Epiſtle vnto <hi>Titus,</hi> cap. 3. <hi>There is no Schiſme that doth not inuent ſome hereſie vnto it ſelfe, that it may ſeeme to haue departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Church vpon a iuſt cauſe.</hi> But tranſubſtantiation which the Catholicks profeſſe, is very far diſtant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe hereſies; for all the properties of a body in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues are ſafe, although they be put in a crum of bread; but the ſame proprieties in order vnto the place which is externall to the body, be ſeperable from it by the diuine omnipotencie, which our School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men explicate ſufficiently. But what hereſie can they find in vs, if we all doe conſtantly confeſſe, that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue as an article of faith that <hi>Chriſt</hi> had, &amp; hath a true body, with all his naturall proprieties in himſelf, which we beleeue, &amp; confeſſe, may be kept by the ſame om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotencie euen whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the body is brought into the leaſt externall place: neither can any impugne this Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally; and humane Philoſophy neither can, nor ought to meaſure the diuine power. Let naturall Philoſophy iudge what may be done by nature; but let her reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and not iudge thoſe things that be aboue nature. Neither doth it follow that the body of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is not in heauen if it be vpon the Altar, we all confeſſe that we
<pb facs="tcp:10328:14"/> beleeue by a diuine faith, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> aſcended into heauen, and there ſitteth continually at the right hand of the Father: But yet we ſay, that by dinine power, one and the ſame body may be in ſundry places at one time, at leaſt ſacramentally: neither can that be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugned but out of humane philoſophie, and apparent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly only. And to conclude, we doe not ſay that bread is made a body which was not before, but we ſay that the bread is tranſubſtantiated into the body of Chriſt, which body was before the conſecration of the bread: ſo likewiſe the body of Chriſt borne of the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was before this tranſubſtantiation, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecration the Bread is tranſubſtantiated into it. Truly they deuiſe out of their owne heads, theſe hereſies ſomething groſſely; for he is an hereticke who main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth hereſie directly; But if they aske of vs what we thinke of the verity of the body of Chriſt, of his aſcention; of his Incarnation; they ſhall receiue from vs a true beliefe in all theſe things; although we af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme ſome things whereon they thinke errours may follow, which we truly denie, and they will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be able to proue Theologically the contrary. Wherefore as for hereſie, they cannot make, or alleage any pretext from hence, why they haue iuſtly and rightfully ſeperated themſelues from our Church.</p>
            <p>11. The milder ſort of Engliſh Proteſtants, who are not infected with Puritaniſme, doe not much charge the <hi>Roman Church</hi> with hereſie; and yet there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they doe not free themſelues from the crime of Schiſme, but they talke much of Idolatrie, and the preſſing of new articles of faith vpon them, wherein they contend that the <hi>Roman Church</hi> and her adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents (that is to ſay, the very <hi>Catholicke Church</hi>) hath reuolted from the true faith; And by this they doe
<pb facs="tcp:10328:14"/> principally defend the equitie of their ſeperation. They eſteeme that it is manifeſt Idolatry to worſhip, and pray vnto Saints, and to reuerence Reliques, and Images, but moſt of all to adore the bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; They ſay likewiſe there is a ſecret Idolatry in the confidence we put in the ſalt, water, and oyle, and other things exerciſed, and bleſſed. They com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine that the Catholicks thruſt vpon them new arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles in ſo many definitions made in the councell of <hi>Trent</hi> about Iuſtification, workes, merits, purgatory, Indulgences, &amp;c. But theſe are vaine words: if wee Catholicks were truly Idolaters, we ſhould not only be hereticks, but much worſe alſo then many here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks; and then we were worthily to be auoyded, and to be caſt out from the ſocyetie of all faithfull people, But I maruell how he that is well in his wits can im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute Idolatry vnto them, who daily profeſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to beleeue in one <hi>God,</hi> and are ready to ſhed their blood for this foundation of faith, who continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally preach that Gods worſhip is not to be giuen to any pure ereature? So this is but a vaine Calumniati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. If for the inuocation of Saints, the worſhip of Images, the adoring of the bleſſed Sacrament, they ſuſpect vs to become guilty of Idolatry, let them but ſeeke, ſearch, and know what we thinke of the vnity of the true <hi>God,</hi> and what of the not giuing diuine ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour vnto creatures, and then they ſhall eaſily finde themſelues to be notorious fooles, who thinke that we be Idolaters, that is adorers of creatures with diuine worſhip, neither ſhould they breake out into ſchiſme vntill they firſt finde in vs true Idolatry.</p>
            <p>12. None of vs at any time ſaid, that holy men al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready dead, or Angels were to be worſhipped with diuine worſhip, we are not yet become ſuch, fooles.
<pb facs="tcp:10328:15"/> 
               <hi>Vigilantius</hi> obiected this againſt the Catholicks in old time but ſlanderouſly, as <hi>S. Hierome</hi> writing againſt him doth declare. As in other things, ſo in this wee haue approued maſters (<hi>viz.</hi>) the old Fathers: we doe not diſſent, we donot depart, we do not diſagree from them; we willingly embrace, and diligently put in practiſe whatſoeuer wholſome catholick precepts the Fathers haue left conferning the Saints, as <hi>Origen. lib. 8. contra Celſum. Epiphanias, hereſ. 79. Auguſtm epiſt. 44. Et lib. de quantitate auimae, ca. 34. Et lib. de vera relig. ca. 55. Et contra fauſtum lib. 20. ca. 21. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Alex. lib. 6. contra Iulian. Theodoret in hiſt. Sanctorum Patrum ca.</hi> 24. whoſe words I cice not at large, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this little booke doth not beare it. From whence therefore haue theſe blinde maſters receiued new eies, ſeeing that long before they were; the holy Catholike Church was perfectly adorned with moſt bright and glorious lights.</p>
            <p>13 Vnto the honour of Saints belong the Feaſts which are celebrated in memory of them, praiſing <hi>God,</hi> and giuing him thankes that he hath preferted mortall men to that high degree of Sanctitie: neither is it a new thing in the Catholicke Church to celebrate feſtiuall daies yeerely in the honour of Saints. It is an ancient thing which may worthily be referred vnto an Apoſtolike tradition, beſides the Lords day to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the birth-dayes of the Saints with feſtiuall ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnities; for I ſee it is approued by the ancient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Catholicke Church: I finde <hi>Cyprian lib. 3. cpiſt.</hi> 6. to haue vſed diligence, that the dayes on which the Martyrs loſt their liues for the faith ſhould be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſet downe, that on ſuch dayes (ſaith he) we may make oblations, and ſacrifices for their commemora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <hi>S. Iohanes Chryſoſtome, ſerm. in Martyrem Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagiam.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:10328:15"/> and <hi>S. Auguſt. pſalm 88. part</hi> 2. in the end doe exhort the people to celebrate deuoutly the ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Saints: wherefore I cannot but much won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at the new ſcruples of the Proteſtants, who will ſeeme to know more then is true, whileſt they eſteeme that the feaſts of all the Saints, and alſo of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> Mother of <hi>God,</hi> and of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and moſt famous Martyrs ought to be abrogated, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in <hi>England</hi> they haue left ſomewhat in this kinde, yet very little.</p>
            <p>14 They ſay it is all one to pray vnto Saints that be dead, and to haue many Gods, and that the inuocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Saints, and worſhipping of Images doth not dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from the cuſtomes of the heathen, for which cauſe they hate vs very much. But it were eaſie for vs if this place would beare a longer diſputation (about the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation of Saints) to refell all the ſlaunders of theſe hereticks, for firſt they are compelled, if they will giue credit vnto the holy Scriptures to grant, that the ſoules of the Saints doe make interceſſion vnto <hi>God</hi> for vs mortall men euen in particular: and it is very well knowne that the faithfull in this life, doe finde helpe before <hi>God</hi> by the prayers of the juſt men here vpon earth: for <hi>Moyſes</hi> many times auerted the anger of <hi>God</hi> from the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> perſwadeth the friends of <hi>Iob ca.</hi> 42. 18. to procure <hi>Iob</hi> to pray for them, that they might obtaine remiſſion of their folly. <hi>Paul</hi> many times commendeth himſelfe to the prayers of the faithfull <hi>Epheſ. 6. 19. Coloſ. 4. 3. 1 Theſſ. 5. 23. 2 Theſſ. 3. 1. Heb. 13. 18. &amp;c.</hi> and they may learne if they will, that the Saints deceaſed whoſe ſoules liue before <hi>God,</hi> and raigne with <hi>Chriſt</hi> make interceſſion for the liuing of the millitant Church, <hi>Hierom. 15. 1. Ezechiol 14. 14. Apoc.</hi> 5. 8. and 8. 3. And it is likewiſe
<pb facs="tcp:10328:16"/> recorded in holy Scriptures that <hi>God</hi> doth grant many things in lauour of his Saints deceaſed, <hi>Gen. 26. 45. 24. Exod. 32. 13. 3. Reg. 18. 36. 1. Paral. 29. 18. 3 Reg.</hi> 11. 12. 32. 34. 15. 4. and 4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 8. 19. &amp; 19. 34. &amp; 20. 6. and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 37. 35. Looke vpon the Comentaries which are called <hi>Chriſoſtomes</hi> hom. 2. pſalm. 50. Chriſt admoniſheth vs to make friends of the Mammon of iniquitie, <hi>Luc. 16. 9. That when you ſhall fasle, they may receiue you into the eternall tabernacles,</hi> and by vertue of this place <hi>S. Auguſtine de cuutate dei lib. 21. ca.</hi> 27. doth attribute much vnto the interceſſion of Saints.</p>
            <p>15 This interceſſion of Saints the Fathers acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, admit, and confirme: and of Angels, the Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Iacob</hi> is knowne. <hi>Gen.</hi> 28. 12. other myſteries of Angels are knowne, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 14. See <hi>Origen</hi> againſt <hi>Celſus lib.</hi> 8. of the <hi>Angels</hi> attending on vs, and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine cpiſt.</hi> 122. and of the <hi>Angell</hi>-keeper the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſpeake very plainly, <hi>Gen. 48. 16. Exod. 23. 20. Pſal. 33. 8. Math. 18. 10. Act. 12. 15.</hi> and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers moſt manifeſtly, <hi>Greg. Wiſſen. de vita Moyſis. Baſil vpon the pſal. 33. Hierom in Math. ca. 18. &amp;c.</hi> And if euery one haue by him the <hi>Angel</hi> of our <hi>Lord,</hi> why ſhould he not call vpon him for helpe. I my ſelfe heard in <hi>England</hi> with great pleaſure, one of my Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of <hi>Windſor</hi> preaching before the King, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely affirming, that there was no cauſe why euery faithfull man ſhould not turne himſelfe vnto his <hi>Angel</hi>-keeper, and ſay, <hi>O holy Angel-keeper pray for me.</hi> Of the interceſsion and Miniſteries of <hi>Angels</hi> for our benefit, you may alſo ſee other Fathers, as <hi>Anthony the father of Monckes, epiſt 2. ad Arſenoitas, Anaſtatius of Synay in Herem. lib. 5. Antiorhus the Abbot hom. 61. Chryſoſtome de incomprehons: des Nat. hom. 3. and
<pb facs="tcp:10328:16"/> hom. in Martyres agiptios. Hierom epiſt. 1. Cirill Alex. apud Anaſtasium Nicenum. queſt. 91. Theodoret</hi> in the ſame place, <hi>Damoſcen lib. 1. Paralel. ca. 7. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>16 But of the interceſsion of the other Saints, we haue the common conſent of the Fathers. <hi>See Cyprian lib. de mortalitate. Hierom againſt Vigilantius Aug. de baptiſmo. lib. 5. ca. 17. lib. 7. ca. 1. and de verbis Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoli. Serm. 47. and Serm. 46. of the Saints, and lib. 9. of his confeſſions cap. 3. lib. de cura pro mortuis cap. 16. and againſt Fanſtus lib, 20. ca. 21. and in his Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, cap. 20-Leo the great Serm. of St. Laurence. Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentius Brix. ſerm. 17. Greg. the great lib. 7. indict. 2. epiſt. 53. Bernard vpon Cant. Cantic. ſerm.</hi> 77. I omit innumerable others that be later. Seeing the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the Fathers, and the vniuerſall conſent of the Church doe certainly affirme that the <hi>Angels,</hi> and ſoules of holy men deceaſed, doe pray for the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and in particular; why then ſhould not euery faithfull man be incouraged to pray vnto them, whom he knoweth for certaine to pray for vs in heauen?</p>
            <p>17 Wherefore it is moſt certaine that this inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Angels,</hi> and Saints (deſiting them to pray for vs, and to ioyne prayer with vs as <hi>St. Chryſoſt.</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, Serm. in <hi>Sanctum Meletium</hi>) cannot be denyed. And we haue very notable examples for vs to pray vnto the bleſſed Virgin, the Mother of <hi>God,</hi> that ſhe would make interceſsion for vs vnto her Sonne; <hi>Irene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um lib. 5. 19. Athan. in Euang. de Deipara. Nazaan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen: orat. in Cyprian: Baſil: Selenciae, Orat. 1. de verbo incarnat. Aug. ſerm. 1. de Anunciat: Coſmam Hieroſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lymi: Sophronium item Hyerofalymi: orat, 6. de Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom, excellencia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>18 And likewiſe the moſt ancient practiſe of the Church doth confirme the imſocation of other Saints.
<pb facs="tcp:10328:17"/> beſides the bleſſed Virgine: ſo that the inuocation of Saints may be derined from an Apoſtolicall Tradition: for the inuocation of Saints was alwayes in vſe, and neuer reprehended of any one, who was not accounted an hereticke. It would be too long here to rehearſe the Fathers who prayed vnto Saints, or them that affirme they are to be prayed vnto: I haue performed it at large in another place, and this perpetuall cuſtome of calling vpon the Saints to pray for vs, and to helpe vs with their prayers, was neuer reprehended; but rather the contrary errour was condemned by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Hierome</hi> againſt <hi>Vigilantius,</hi> which condemnation the whole Church approued: Therefore by the iudgement of all the holy Church, our new <hi>Vigilantians</hi> are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, whoſe raſhneſſe is very great, whileſt they imagine a crime of Idolatry in our inuocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Saints. Neither haue theſe <hi>Vigilantians</hi> any ſollid argument, or obiection to make againſt this inuocation. All their obiections I haue anſwered fully in another place; as alſo I thinke that I haue ſufficiently defended the vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of holy Reliques in another place, which Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques <hi>God</hi> hath confirmed to be gratefull vnto him by manifeſt myracles.</p>
            <p>19 But our aduerſaries doe conſtantly affirme, that in the worſhip of holy Images we commit Idolatry, and for this cauſe they pretend that their departure from vs is iuſt: but this their pretext is moſt vaine; neither can they by this free themſelues from the foule brand of filthy Schiſme; for if we reuerence holy Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges with any proper honour, beſides the honour and worſhip which is due to the firſt patterne; that is not the honour and worſhip of <hi>Latria,</hi> nor that true adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is due to <hi>God</hi> alone. Therefore when wee moſt clearely profeſſe that godly honour and the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb facs="tcp:10328:17"/> of <hi>Latria</hi> is due, neither to Saints, nor to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, or Images, why doe they obiect vnto vs Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try? the vſe of Images doth belong vnto Eccleſiaſticall ceremonies; but as much as concerneth theſe things, the ſafe, certaine, and infallible rule to know whither they be lawfull or no, is the practiſe and vſe of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church; ſo that all thoſe rites be lawfull, and good, which either the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelues, or Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall men haue inſtiuted, or elſe haue allowed with ſilence, or expreſſe leaue. But it is moſt certaine that the Chriſtian Church, yea the moſt auncient, and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall, with a full conſent without any oppoſition, or any contradiction hath worſhipped, and reuerenced pictures and holy Images. <hi>Iohn Damaſcenus</hi> hath col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected great ſtore of teſtimonies in the three Orations which he wrote for Images, and ſo did the Fathers of the ſeauenth generall <hi>Synod,</hi> and after-them many lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Catholicks of later times. Therefore what vpſtart Nouice dare condemne that, which the moſt holy and learned Fathers haue commended, taught, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, that which the Catholick Church it ſelfe taught by the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and hath kept in all times, that which <hi>God</hi> himſelfe hath alſo diuers times confirmed with myracles. Are not they then (according to the ſaying of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) moſt inſolent and mad, who doe not<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 118.</note> retaine and keepe deuoutly: but caſt away, and reiect the vſe of Images together with their due honor, when neither the worſhip of <hi>Latria,</hi> which is due to <hi>God,</hi> nor of <hi>Dulia,</hi> which is due vnto the Saints themſelues, is giuen vnto them.</p>
            <p>20 Our aduerſaries chiefly vrge two arguments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this our worſhipping of holy Images, which they thinke ſo ſtrong, as that they imagine we can by no meanes auoyde them, and free our ſelues from the
<pb facs="tcp:10328:18"/> crime of Idolatry; and by theſe they confirme their Schiſme to be lawfull. The one is the commandement of <hi>God,</hi> forbidding Images to bee made: The other, that they who doe adore the true <hi>God</hi> in any externall ſigne which is a pure creature, cannot be excuſed from extreame Idolatry: for, they ſay with <hi>Caluine,</hi> that the Calfe was made by the children of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> Exod. 32. 4. to repreſent the true <hi>God.</hi> And in this poynt, eſpecially <hi>Raynolds</hi> the Engliſh man, an earneſt Puritane, ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theneth and foundeth his Treatiſe of the Idolatry of the <hi>Romane Church:</hi> But I doe not doubt, neither can the learned Aduerſaries doubt, that the moſt auncient holy Fathers, and the Catholicke Church it ſelfe did know the commandements, and the Hiſtory of the Calfe, and neuertheleſſe without all difficulty, or any ſcruple, they vſed holy Images in euery place with worſhip and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. But this diſputation becommeth not this little booke, and I hope I ſhall haue oportunity hereafter to confute at large <hi>Raynolds</hi> booke of the Idolatry of the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> by the authority of which booke, <hi>England</hi> doth now chiefly defend her Schiſme. In the meane ſpace, let me change a fewe words with them. I deſire them to remember the works of <hi>Salomon,</hi> who indued with heauenly wiſedome, beautified the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which he built not onely with thoſe Images, and artificiall workes which <hi>God</hi> himſelfe had commanded to be made, ſuch as were the Cherubims, &amp;c. but alſo of his owne deuiſe added many Images, and engrauen trees and beaſts, as braſen Bulles, Palmes, and Pome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granets; and adorned alſo his throne with Lyons, and Lyons whelpes of gold. 3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 10. 19. 20, &amp;c. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Salomon</hi> vnderſtood and expounded vnto vs ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently, that the precept of the <hi>Decalog</hi> forbidding grauen Images, was neither perpetuall, nor yet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden
<pb facs="tcp:10328:18"/> by the diuiue naturall law (which prohibiteth the adoration of <hi>Latria</hi> towards Images) but onely of the law of <hi>God</hi> poſitiue, for a time and conditionall to be kept then, and ſo long, as there was preſent danger of committing Idolatry by hauing Images. Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no danger of committing Idolatry in Images by vs, who are well inſtructed: Therefore that prohibition of the <hi>Decalog</hi> which forbiddeth ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes to be made, hath no place amongſt vs: and for this cauſe the <hi>Iconomochi</hi> abolliſhing the vſe of holy Images, and breaking them, and abuſing them vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerendly, were in all times accounted by the Catholick Church for peſtilent wicked hereticks, and reckoned amongſt the Enemies of Chriſtian religion.</p>
            <p>21 It is moſt certaine that the children of <hi>Iſraell</hi> committed Idolatry in the adoration of the Calfe; but I will neuer graunt that the Calfe did onely repreſent vnto them the true <hi>God;</hi> And it is moſt falſe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the true ſence of the holy Scripture, to affirme that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did adore the true <hi>God</hi> in that Calfe. They adored the golden Calfe it ſelfe, and erring moſt wickedly, they thought that it had the Diuinity of the true <hi>God:</hi> And I doe not doubt but that I ſhall eaſily demonſtrate this out of moſt plaine places of the holy Scripture in his time and place, and then I will diſſolue the ſubtill reaſons of <hi>Caluin</hi> and <hi>Reynolds,</hi> and ſhew that the true <hi>God</hi> may euen in corporall ſignes be ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with compleat <hi>Latria<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> without all danger of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting Idolatry, to the end that it may more mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly appeare, that the Engliſh are groſly deceiued while they dreame by the fopperies of <hi>Reynalds,</hi> to triumph ouer the Catholick <hi>Romane Church,</hi> as fallen into Idolatry, and therefore iuſtly forſaken by them. Seeing there is neither euill circumſtance, nor ſcandall
<pb facs="tcp:10328:19"/> in our vſe of holy Images; becauſe we liue not amongſt Idolaters, and are, or may be ſufficiently inſtructed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their lawfull worſhip, how farre it is different from true <hi>Latria,</hi> therfore we may lawfully fall downe before an Image, and ſo adore with true <hi>Latria</hi> the primatiue patterne, if it be to be adored with true <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria;</hi> As the children of <hi>Iſraell</hi> did, when they adored <hi>God</hi> in the cloud, at the dore of the Tabernacle, and did not adore the cloud, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33. 10. and when they ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him in the fire. 2. <hi>Paralip.</hi> 7. 3. and yet herein they did not commit any Idolatry, though they adored <hi>God</hi> in corporall ſignes. They therefore who condemne ſuch like adoration as truly and properly Idolatricall, are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of all true and ſollid Diuinity: Therefore in vaine doe the Proteſtants cauill at this Idolatry, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend their Schiſme and ſeperation from the <hi>Romane-Church,</hi> and hereby firſt they pollute themſelues with manifeſt hereſie, and remaine true Schiſmaticks for that herein there was no lawfull cauſe of ſeperation.</p>
            <p>22 They doe obiect vnto vs a moſt open Idolatry in adoring the B. Sacrament, for that we adore it with true <hi>Latria,</hi> and by this alſo our Aduerſaries doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe themſelues from Schiſmes: But they are much deceiued; for we are moſt certaine, that the reall and corporall preſence of the body and blood of our Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> in the holy myſteries of the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> is preſent: we adore the very body of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which is to be adored with true <hi>Latria</hi> of it ſelfe, by reaſon of the hypoſtaticall vnion lying hid vnder the formes of bread and wine: but this queſtion doth not belong vnto this place. Wee ſuppoſe this reall and corporall preſence, which ſuppoſition is aſſured vnto vs by faith, for that we take it from the Goſpell, <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaying, when hee held the Bread in his hands, <hi>This is my body,</hi> according
<pb facs="tcp:10328:19"/> to the promiſe he had made, ſaying, <hi>Ioan. 6. 51. The bread which I will giue is my fleſh.</hi> Wherefore our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries cannot ſo much as imagine that we in this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration are guilty of Idolatry, and therefore they cannot aleage it in any excuſe of their ſchiſme. But they are not only truly and properly Schiſmaticks but alſo hereticks: and therefore I was bound of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to forſake them, vnleſſe <hi>I</hi> would haue conſented vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their errours.</p>
            <p>23 They impute vnto vs ſecret Idolatry, for that we place a ſpirituall confidence in ſalt, water, oyle, and the like after exorciſmes and benedictions; But theſe things they heape together, to the intent that they may diſgrace, and defame vs, and excuſe their ſchiſme by what meanes ſoeuer; for they know well, that we doe not put any certaine confidence in theſe things, as if we thought that theſe creatures receiued any certaine, and infallible force, or power by our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orciſmes, and benedictions: and we doe not call theſe things Sacraments, but holy things which we vſe for the increaſe of our deuotion, and put all our confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in God alone, who hearing the prayers of his Church doth diſtribute his gifts by theſe creatures through the vertue of the ſame prayers and benedicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his Church; And the greateſt part of theſe and ſuch like rites we haue receiued from Apoſtolicall Tradition, and ſucceſſion from the moſt ancient Church, which who ſo followeth cannot erre, and he who contemneth and reiecteth ſuch things, is to be caſt out as an haire-brained enemy of the Church, <hi>Tertullian lib. de Baptiſmo</hi> ſetteth downe the vſe of hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed oyle, <hi>Auguſt. epiſt.</hi> 119. numbereth alſo oyle amongſt holy things. The conſecration of water for baptiſme, hath beene kept time out of minde in the
<pb facs="tcp:10328:20"/> Church; for <hi>Cyprian lib. 1. epiſt. vlt.</hi> maketh mention of the water, and oyle of conſecration, and anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. We haue in <hi>Optatus Miliuitanus.</hi> That the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">Lib. 2. c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e: Par ent.</note> Temples if they were polluted, by any meanes were wont to be hallowed againe with exorciſmes, and waſhing of the walls, <hi>St. Baſil</hi> deduceth from tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib. de Spirita Sanct. ca.</hi> 27.</note> the vſuall rite of annointing the baptized with oyle. Antiquity teacheth that the ſigne of the croſſe was wont to be vſed in the hallowings, and conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of all things. <hi>Iuſtin queſt. 118. Nazianzen, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat.</hi> 1. againſt <hi>Iulian,</hi> and in the Orat. at the Funerall of his Father <hi>Chryſost. 55. in Matheum. Auguſt. tract. 118. in Ioan.</hi> and ſerm. 3. of the Annunciation, and <hi>ſerm. de tempore 181. cap. 3. Areopagita</hi> and others. There are perhaps amongſt vs ſome Rytes not ſo anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, in which we vſe hallowed, and conſecrated things: but ſeeing the Primatiue Church inſtructed by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> feared no danger of ſecret Idolatry, when ſhe vſed conſecrated oyle, and the like, why ſhould we now feare, who attribute no more vnto theſe conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated things, then the old Antiquity did vnto theirs? Therefore to runne into ſchiſme for theſe things is great impiety. Theſe rites are good, ſeeing moſt of them are inſtituted by the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and others ſprung forth from the deuotion of Catholicke Churches, and all are in no part contrary to faith; but rather conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant vnto faith. There was in old time diuerſity of rytes, and ceremonies in diuers Churches, and yet they did not therefore depart from a mutuall Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For as <hi>Sozominus</hi> ſaith, <hi>They eſteemed it to be fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous, and that worthily, that they who agree together in the principall heads, or points of Religion, ſhould be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated one from another, for the difference of a Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</hi> Therefore the ſeperation of the Engliſh (by which
<pb facs="tcp:10328:20"/> they haue deuided themſelues from the true Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Church, and broken out into a manifeſt ſchiſme) is friuolous, raſh, and impious; And to communicate with them in diuine matters, is to conſent vnto their moſt wicked, and peſtiferous ſchiſme.</p>
            <p>24 I will not here (for feare of being too long) diſpute of the ſuppoſed new articles, whereupon they ground their complaints, and endeuour to excuſe their ſchiſme: But will reſerue this matter to be handled in another place. Now I aske them this queſtion. Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they thinke that thoſe which they call new articles be contrary to faith or no? if they ſhould be contrary to faith, then they ſhould be hereſies, and ſhould make vs heretickes worthily to be auoyded, and to be ſeperated from the Communion of the catholicke Church. But I haue proued already that there is no hereſie in the Catholicke <hi>Roman Church,</hi> and the Kings <hi>Maieſtie</hi> of great <hi>Britaine,</hi> and many learned men in that kingdome haue confeſſed, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth not faile, or erre in fundamentall points of faith; and I haue already proued before, that there is no true article which is not fundamentall, and to be firmely beleeued; therefore it maintaineth no articles which are contrary to the Catholicke faith; and ſince they be not contrary to the true faith: but containe the true faith, they cannot miniſter a iuſt cauſe to begin a ſchiſme. But Proteſtants ſay the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth ſeperate, and deuide vs from her, becauſe we reſpect thoſe articles. But <hi>I</hi> am ſorry, and lament, that they had made a moſt foule, and groſſe ſchiſme before any thing was ſpoken of concerning theſe arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles which they call new; Therefore it is great folly in them to alleage theſe new articles, as a cloake for their ſchiſme; for the effect cannot goe before his
<pb facs="tcp:10328:21"/> cauſe. <hi>I</hi> defend that they haue made a ſchiſme with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe, and by this <hi>I</hi> knew that they were manifeſt ſchiſmatickes, and therefore haue departed from them. And thoſe ſame articles which Proteſtants affirme to be new, may be euidently demonſtrated out of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Traditions, and Fathers to be true; and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary articles which they ſet downe may be conuinced out of them to containe manifeſt hereſies, If the ſence of the firſt Authors be retained: for ſome milder Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants now of late in matters of Controuerſie (as <hi>I</hi> haue heard) doe vſe fauourable explications, not much diſſonant from Catholicke doctrine, by which they ſeeme to tend to a pious Reconciliation.</p>
            <p>Who without a pernitious errour, or rather plaine hereſie, can put all his ſaluation in faith only, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the neceſſitie of good workes, and abſolutely denie our merits; and affirme that grace once had can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be loſt, and that the iuſt cannot ſinne? They who hold with tooth, and nayle, that theſe, and the like are articles of faith; and that the contrary are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, doe without queſtion erre in matters of faith, and declare themſelues to be hereticks, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence are worthily numbred amongſt hereticks by Catholicks in their definitions: Therefore not any he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or her manifeſt, or ſecret Idolatry could giue an occaſion vnto the Proteſtants ſchiſme. Neither can they obiect ſchiſme vnto the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> for ſhe made not the ſchiſme, but they made it, and ſhe endured it: for, from her <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Caluin,</hi> and the reſt ſeperated themſelues firſt, and not ſhe from them. When they obſtinatly reiected the Iudgement of the Church, then they made a ſchiſme. Then they deuided the Coate of Chriſt, then they er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected one Altar againſt another, then they forſooke the true Church.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10328:21"/>
            <p>25 Beſides the cauſes before rehearſed, and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, they alſo pretended for their ſchiſme, a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of Reformation in the Church; But I could neuer yet ſee any reformation amongſt them: but to ſay the truth I obſerued many deformations: for the care of conſcience is vtterly neglected, and caſt away amongſt them; ſome few accepted, the reſt haue no ſcruple of conſcience to commit adultery; violent extertion, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherie againſt their neighbours, coſenage, vſury; as people who haue impiouſly abolliſhed auricular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, faſtings, penance, and ſuch like holy exerciſes. And ſuppoſe that they had found amongſt vs any thing to be reprehended either in our manners, or in our actions, or in our gouernment, that ſhould not be imputed to the defects of the Church, but vnto par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular men, whoſe actions are not allowed; but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by Catholicks, neither ought they to haue rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a filthy ſchiſme for thoſe ſmaller matters, when the foundation of faith remained firme, ſtable, and vnſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> And ſuppoſe that we had builded vpon it, <hi>Wood, ſtubble, or Hay,</hi> as it is ſaid in 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 12. Yet we ſhould not be excluded from ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. But the Proteſtants haue left the foundation, they haue forſaken the foundation it ſelfe: and the gold, and ſiluer, and pretious ſtones which they vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brag of, and vaunt to be theirs, are more baſe then the filth and mire in the ſtreets, vnleſſe they be built vpon the true foundation which is <hi>Chriſt.</hi> There is one foundation; not two foundations; one Church, not two; one Chriſt not two. If Chriſt be our foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which they cannot deny, then he is not theirs; They haue made another Church deuided and ſeperated from ours, and that cannot be the Church, for that the Church is one and not two; He that will be a member
<pb facs="tcp:10328:22"/> of that Church, muſt needs be without the true Church of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>26 I confeſſe that the Engliſh Proteſtants deceiued me, before that I had exactly conſidered the nature of a ſchiſme; for when I obiected ſchiſme vnto them, ſome anſwered that it was not their fault, that they did not communicate with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> they were ready to be in vnion, but the Pope would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them into his communion, but reiected them with an <hi>anathema.</hi> This excuſe ſeemed to me for a time to be iuſt, and reaſonable, but after I begun out of this ground in my priuate arguments, and publike Sermons to vrge an vnion, which vpon their words ſeemed to me ſomewhat eaſily to be concluded; and ſo thruſt my finger further into the wound; then I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued that in <hi>England</hi> they did not vſe the Engliſh confeſſion (or authoriſed articles) for a rule of their faith, (which as they affirmed were very modeſt.) But the Confeſsion of <hi>Caluin,</hi> and many groſſe errours of <hi>Luther.</hi> And this I perceiued more euidently, when I looked into the counterfeit Sinod of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants at <hi>Dort,</hi> in which the puritanicall articles of <hi>Caluine</hi> by conſent of the Engliſh Agents were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, with the good liking of the Engliſh ſect. And if the Engliſh confeſsion which is deuided into certaine articles doth not include in them thoſe puritanicall ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of <hi>Dort,</hi> why did they giue their conſent, and voyces vnto the <hi>Caluinian</hi> exceſſes in the name of the Engliſh ſect? Moreouer, how can they, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe themſelues mortall Enemyes to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> be thought to deſire an vnion with the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and that the defect of agreement is not on their parts? How can they caſt the cauſes of ſchiſme vpon the curſes of <hi>Rome,</hi> and Councell of Trident,
<pb facs="tcp:10328:22"/> when before the ſaid curſes they had deuided them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues by ſchiſme, from the Catholicke Church: and by ſuch a ſchiſme as in ſome reſpect was farre worſe, and more foule, then was the ſchiſme which was firſt raiſed by <hi>Luther,</hi> and increaſed by <hi>Caluine?</hi> For that England at the beginning abſtained from the opinions of <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Caluine,</hi> neither did they charge the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> either with hereſie, or Idolatry (which the <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Caluiniſts</hi> made the pretext of their ſchiſme) and yet neuertheleſſe, without any appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent cauſe, long after, they yealded vnto the common ſchiſme of theſe hereticks: And now at this time, the Engliſhmen (for the moſt part) doe not onely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, and defend the deuiſion, and ſeperation made, but ſtriue by all force to maintaine it: for they flye backe from vnion, caſt away charity, and doe all they can to hinder peace, and brotherly Loue, in ſuch ſort, as that many of them ſay, they will ſooner, and more willingly enter into allyance or league with the Turks, then with the Papiſts. Call you this a minde ready to agree or to make an attonement? is it likely to be true that the fault is not theirs why they doe not communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with the <hi>Romane Church?</hi> No, it cannot poſſibly be, that the vnion whereof I had ſome hope ſhould take effect, except they doe firſt deteſt all hereſies, and heretickes, and beleeue aright with the Catholicke <hi>Roman Church,</hi> and be conioyned vnto it in perfect Charitie.</p>
            <p>27 <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. made little difference but with the Pope onely, whoſe primacie he denied, with an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall ſpirit, and moued with ſome diſtempered hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, violently tooke vnto himſelfe onely the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall ſupremacie, and carried himſelfe more mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatly in other things which belonged vnto the faith, and
<pb facs="tcp:10328:23"/> diuine ſeruice, and ceremonies of the Catholicke Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Vnder <hi>Edward</hi> his ſonne a childe, and much more vnder <hi>Elizabeth</hi> they departed not onely from the <hi>Pope,</hi> the Vicar of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſupreame Paſtor of the whole Chriſtian ſlocke, but alſo the diuine ſeruice, and worſhip of <hi>God,</hi> was taken away from the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks by maine force and iniury, and forbidden by the publique ſecular lawes. What, was there any lawfull Synode firſt called? were the obiections againſt the Catholicks examined and diſcuſſed? were their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers heard? were they conuicted of any errour, or impiety in Religion? was the iudgement giuen by any competent Iudge? No ſuch matter. Doth not the ſame violence, the ſame iniury, the ſame impietie continue? for what labour and paines doe they (who haue the chiefe charge of their Religion in <hi>England</hi> ſuch as it is) daily take, leaſt that the diuine, anncient, pious, and preſcript ſeruice, ſhould be reſtored vnto Catholicks? And are not they then in the fault, that the Schiſme is not taken away? They vrge Reformation; yet Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation although it be iuſt, and neceſſary, if it be done with Schiſme, is a moſt foule, &amp; hatefull deformation. That is reformed, which continuch the ſame in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: Therefore the Catholicke Religion, and her ſubſtantiall exerciſes, ought to haue remained in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> and if any thing therein had been to be reformed, it ſhould haue beene put vnder a lawfull reformation (<hi>ſeruatis ſeru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ndes</hi>) without taking away neceſſaries: And they ſhould not haue brought in another Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſuppreſſed the former, or thruſt it into a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, thereby to make two contrary, and repugnant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions: ſo as the firſt is not reformed, but as much as in them lyeth leſtroyed, and a new forged. Moreouer, there cannot be two Religions of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but one onely
<pb facs="tcp:10328:23"/> which is ours, as I haue ſhewed, becauſe there is but one Church, one foundation, and one <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>28. Therefore when amongſt other euils, I ſaw my ſelfe enuironed on euery ſide with an inuetterate Schiſme, and that there was no hope of vnion: an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar being erected againſt an Altar, and diſioyned from the charity of the Church; I neither ought, nor could ſtay with them any longer with a ſafe conſcience: Wherefore the remorſe of conſcience compelled me to returne vnto the <hi>Catholicke Church;</hi> My <hi>Agar</hi> hearing the voyce of the <hi>Angell</hi> reprouing her, and ſaying: <hi>Returne vnto thy Miſtris, and humble thy ſelfe vnder</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 16. 9</note> 
               <hi>her hand:</hi> was forced of neceſſity to returne vnto the moſt holy Church her Miſtris. Moreouer, my ſlight could bring me nothing, but ſhame, and deſtruction. <hi>God</hi> commaunded me to be humble vnder the hand of my Miſtris, and in this thing eſpecially it behooued me to follow <hi>God.</hi> I wiſh to God that they vnto whom I fooliſhly fled, would acknowledge their moſt miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpirituall eſtate, not onely for their hereſies, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for their lamentable Schiſme, from which as I haue ſhewed them they cannot be excuſed, becauſe they haue ſeperated themſelues vniuſtly, and without cauſe from the true Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which is our <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Romane</hi> Church; And this thing terriſieth me: for Schiſmaticks exclude themſelues from being the ſonnes. of <hi>God,</hi> as <hi>Cyprian</hi> affirmeth, ſaying; <hi>They haue not God</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 11. 52. <hi>De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>to their Father, who will not haue the</hi> (true) <hi>Church for their mother. Chriſt</hi> died <hi>to gather into one the ſonnes of God which were diſperſed.</hi> Therefore the death of <hi>Chriſt</hi> did not onely worke, and doth worke the redemption of men, but alſo the vnion of the Church. Before the death of <hi>Chriſt</hi> the children of <hi>God</hi> were deuided and ſcattered, ſome vnder the law of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> others vnder
<pb facs="tcp:10328:24"/> the law of nature; all were deuided one from another into ſeuerall congregations. But now ſince the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the diuine wiſedome would that all his faithfull beleeuer, and true children by faith, ſhould make one onely ſocietie throughout the whole world, vnder their Captaine, and Emperour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and ſerue him in his warres vnder the ſtandard of the holy Croſſe, with the ſame colours and Enſignes of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments. And this ſociety and vnity is a notable ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the death of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which death hath brought to paſſe, that diſagreeing Sects, &amp; innumerable formes of Rites, and Religions amongſt themſelues oppoſite, ſhould ioyne together into a Chriſtian vnity by him, <hi>Who is our peace, and hath made both one,</hi> and this <hi>by the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 2. 14. <hi>Lib. 3. Hexem.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Croſſe,</hi> whereupon <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> of <hi>Mount Sinay</hi> ſaith, that theſe words, <hi>Let waters be gathered into one place,</hi> are to be vnderſtood of the Church, aſſembled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of diuers people, and Nations, and Sects, vnder the vnity of faith: For which cauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> alſo ſaid of his <hi>Croſſe, If I be exalted from the earth, I will draw all</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 12. 32.</note> 
               <hi>things vnto my ſelfe. Athanaſius</hi> in his Treatiſe of the Incarnation of the word of <hi>God,</hi> ſayeth, <hi>Our Lord ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted in the Croſſe, ſtretcheth forth both his armes to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite vnto himſelfe onely, both the Nations of the Iewes and Gentiles, that by embracing them, he might gather them both into his boſome:</hi> but there is but one onely boſome betweene the armes of our <hi>Sauiour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>29 And <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in the ſame place thinketh, that it is not without myſterie, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> did chooſe the death of the Croſſe, and not the cutting off his head, by which his precurſor S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> loſt his life, nor the deuiding of his body into parts, which <hi>I ſaie</hi> ſuffered: <hi>that in his death he might without diſmembring keepe his body whole and intire, and take away all excuſes from
<pb facs="tcp:10328:24"/> Schiſmaticks, who deſire to deuide the Church into parts.</hi> And <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Lord was ſo pleaſed with this vnity, that with a moſt ſeruent prayer in the very laſt night of his life, he required of his Father, that he would not ſuffer his Diſciples, and the other beleeuers to depart from this vnity: and ſaid twice, that the cauſe why he<note place="margin">Ioan. 17. 11. 20. 21.</note> prayed for the preſeruation of this vnity was: <hi>That the world may beleeue that thou haſt ſent me.</hi> But our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries nothing conſidering theſe things, as much as lyeth in them, would haue the death and croſſe of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to be without this moſt excellent fruit of vnity; and by deuiſions and ſchiſmes giue vnto the Iewes and Pagans occaſion to ſpeake ill of, and to blaſpheme <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by ſaying that he was not the ſonne of <hi>God,</hi> nor ſent by <hi>God,</hi> ſeeing the vnion which he ordained did not continue, but now and then was broken into parts. The Church of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is one houſe, and one family; he who ſhall withdraw himſelfe from this family, or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth out of this houſe, doth not appertaine vnto the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but is excluded from ſaluation, euen as they who were without the Arke, periſhed in the flood.<note place="margin">Gen. 8</note> The Proteſtants haue cut off themſelues from the body of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which is the ſole <hi>Catholicke Romane Church,</hi> with her inſeperable adherents: Therefore there be not members of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> nor is <hi>Chriſt</hi> their head; neither are they partakers of his holy ſpirit, or gifts. They are rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten members, and already cut off, for that they haue by their owne free will impiouſly cut off themſelues from the body. <hi>They are branches cut off from the Vine, good for nothing but for the fire: Neither can he</hi> (ſaith <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Auguſtine) be partaker of Diuine charity, who is an enemie of vnity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>30 By Schiſme they haue inenrred the loſſe of all ſpirituall goods, if they thinke they poſſeſſe any; <hi>If I
<pb facs="tcp:10328:25"/> ſpeake</hi> (ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul) with the tongues of men and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 1.</note> 
               <hi>and haue not charity, I am nothing: it doth profit me nothing, &amp;c.</hi> According to theſe words of <hi>St. Paul St. Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, that Schiſmatickes doe not profit<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 1. de Bapt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 2.</note> by doing good workes. <hi>Cyprian</hi> affirmeth the ſame many times, ſaying, <hi>Although a man be ſlaine for the name of Chriſt after he is out of his Church, and deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from vnity, and charity, he cannot be crowned in his death,</hi> and repeateth the ſame <hi>lib. 1. epiſt.</hi> 1. and vnto <hi>Iuba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>num,</hi> and in his bookes <hi>de Simplicitate Praeleth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> or, <hi>de vnitate Eccleſiae,</hi> and <hi>de oratione dommica, Chriſoſtom in epiſt. ad Epheſ. hom.</hi> 11. followeth him, and ſaith the ſame.</p>
            <p>31 I wiſh they would conſider what a horrible ſin they haue committed, by making this damnable ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. For that Schiſme is the deſtruction of holy Church according to the words of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſaying, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Kingdome euided against it ſelfe be made de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk. 11. 17. Galat.</hi> 5. 15.</note> And <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Take heed, how you bite one another, leaſt you be conſumed one with another,</hi> and <hi>St.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib. depoenit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> proueth, that this wickedneſſe of deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Church, may be that ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt, which <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid is not remitted, neither in this<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat. 12. 31. 3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 6.</note> world, nor in the world to come. So that wicked har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot had rather to haue the childe deſtroyed, then to be reſtored into the boſome of the owne mother, and therefore cryed againſt her, <hi>be it neither mine nor thine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>but let it be deuided.</hi> So Schiſmatickes, leaſt the faith ſhould be conſcrued aliue, and whole in the boſome of the true mother the Church, doe what they can to deuide it, that it may be dead to them both. But they labour in vaine, to the verifying vpon themſelues this ſaying, <hi>He that breaketh the hedge, a Serpent ſhall byte him.</hi> And it is no wonder that in theſe dayes the
<pb facs="tcp:10328:25"/> Engliſh are fallen into many hereſies, and that Purita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme doth ſo much raigne amongſt them, although at the firſt ſeperation, they were not polluted with the <hi>Lutheran</hi> or <hi>Caluinian</hi> hereſies: For <hi>Ireneus</hi> doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. cap. 40. &amp; li. 4. ca.</hi> 43.</note> teach, that they who are cut off from the Church, doe not drinke of the Fountaine of the ſpirit of <hi>God:</hi> but digge vnto themſelues olde Ciſterns, and fall into moſt filthy errours againſt the true faith. And ſo <hi>Gyprian</hi> maketh the Catholicke Church a Roote, a<note place="margin">Lib. de ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>p. Pralater. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Fountaine, a Sunne, ſo that as the braunch hath life from the roote, the Brooke hath water from the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, the rayes light from the Sunne, euen ſo the ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of faith cannot be had, but by coniunction to the Catholicke Church. They therefore who haue ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated themſelues from it, cannot receiue the verity of faith, but of neceſſity they muſt fall into errours; for they be trees without a roote, they be Brookes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Fountaine, and Rayes without a Sunne. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon the Fathers in many places by theſe, and the like reaſons doe manifeſtly proue, that Schiſme doth at length breake out into hereſie: For hee who doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to haue communion with the <hi>Catholick Church:</hi> he alſo will refuſe to learne of it the verities of Faith, of which ſhee onely is the keeper and conſeuer. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore very well did <hi>Auguſtine</hi> conclude, <hi>That an inuet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cont. Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſcon. lib. 2. cap. 7. Lib. 1. epiſt.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>Schiſme is euen hereſie it ſelfe.</hi> And rightly did <hi>Cyprian</hi> finde in euery Schiſme this hereſie at leaſt, that by it are taken away theſe two articles out of the Creed: <hi>I beleeue the holy Catholick Church,</hi> and <hi>the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes.</hi> For they that beleeue the holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Church to be the true Church of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> cannot depart from the ſame, if they ſo beleeue: But if they doe depart, certainly they doe not beleeue, that the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Church is the true Church of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> So <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:10328:26"/> ſaith, that the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> had turned the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Schiſme into an hereſie. And <hi>Ambroſe</hi> approuing his fact, who had fled from the Churches of the <hi>Luciferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> haue now done from the Engliſh, ſaid: <hi>Hee thought there was no faith in the Schiſme, for though they kept the faith to God, yet they did not keepe it to the Church, whoſe limbes they ſuffered</hi> (as it were) <hi>to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, and members to be rent in pieces<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for ſeeing Chriſt d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſufer for the Church, and the Church is Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, they ſeeme not to beleeue Chriſt, who make his paſſion voyde, and teare his body in peeces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>33. Should I therefore haue ſtayed among Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matickes, and hereticks with ſuch danger vnto my ſoule? God forbid. I repent me with all my heart, that I haue remained ſo long amongſt them, and haue taken vp and vſed wicked Armes againſt my Mother, the Catholicke truth, and haue written bookes of the <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Common-wealth</hi> full of hereſies, which I ſincerely hete, and deteſt, and was a Souldier in that graceleſſe Campe to the perpetuall infamy of mine owne name; And now it doth both grieue, and vexe me, that I haue beene the Author of ſo great wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Therefore with all humility and reuerence, I aske and craue pardon and forgiueneſſe for my wicked offence of <hi>God</hi> Almighty, of <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Sauiour, and of the <hi>Pope</hi> his Soueraigne, and chiefe Viccar vpon earth; and doe wholy ſubmit my ſelfe; and faults vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the great clemency of the ſame <hi>Pope,</hi> who ſitteth ſupreme Iudge of vs all, and not to be iudged of any vpon Earth, for that he repreſenteth the perſon of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his Church. And euen as our <hi>Lord</hi> himſelfe doth open willingly his boſome of mercy vnto him that is penitent, ſo am I in good hope that I ſhall bee receiued into the armes of the Clemency of his holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.
<pb facs="tcp:10328:26"/> The example of <hi>St. Cyprian</hi> againſt <hi>Stephen</hi> the Pope (much reproued and condemned in the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Church) ſome times confirmed me in my wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, of ſtriuing, and reſiſting againſt the ſupreme <hi>Paſtor;</hi> But now my foule fall hath taught me to my loſſe, that thoſe Biſhops wander, and goe aſtray from the right path of Faith, who doe refuſe to be guided by the only Pole-ſtarre which is the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> to follow wandering fiery Meteors to their deſtruction. Would to <hi>God</hi> euen as the diuine <hi>Cyprian</hi> by the effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his owne blood for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> did waſh away the ſtaine of his former Audacity, ſo I heartily deſire that there might be giuen vnto me (who in the multitude and hainouſneſſe of my faults haue ſurpaſſed incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably his fall) the oportunitie and grace, to deface and blot out my foule ſtaines and filthineſſe, and beare witneſſe of the truth of the Catholicke faith with the ſhedding of my very blood: which ſtaines and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe I am moſt ready <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the helpe of <hi>God</hi> when Inke ſhould faile, to ſigne with my proper blood, to the praiſe and glory of <hi>God,</hi> the Exaltation of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Catholicke Church,</hi> and to the honour, and dignity of the <hi>Apoſtolike Sea,</hi> which God grant.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>At Rome.</hi> 
                  <date>24. <hi>Nouembris. Anno.</hi> 1622.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:10328:27"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10328:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:10328:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10328:28"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:10328:29"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:10328:29"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:10328:30"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:10328:30"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:10328:31"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:10328:31"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:10328:32"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:10328:32"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:10328:33"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:10328:33"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:10328:34"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:10328:34"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:10328:35"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:10328:35"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
